James Gross NLRB Files /4057
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series III. NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD 7/35-11/47
  - Sub-Series A. NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD RECORDS
    - Sub-Series 2. CORRESPONDENCE 7/19/35-3/19/70
      - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 21)
        7/1/36-9/30/36; Correspondence from Herber Blankenhorn and J. Warren Madden to the Board, Robert LaFollette, regional officers, and Harold Cranefield concerning the LaFollette Investigation, includes a summary of the plan of investigation adopted by the Senate sub-committee, and a list of subpoenas served, as well as reports from investigators in cities; from John J. Babe (attorney) to Hon. John J. Parker (Chief Judge, U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals) on the question of the separability of the National Labor Relations Act; Edwin S. Smith's and Charles H. Logan's (Director, Region 15) discussion of Mr. Ryan; from Charles Fahy to John J. Parker, Elliott Northcott, Morris A. Soper (Judges, U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals) concerning the NLRB versus Washington, Virginia and Maryland Coach Co.; correspondence regarding Mercer Evans and Rev. Francis J. Haas as successors to John Carmody; correspondence concerning the RCA and the Virginia Railway case, specifically the enforcement of the Byrnes Act; from Madden to Harwood L. Childs (Managing Editor, Public Opinion Quarterly) responding to a prospectus of the publication; A. Howard Myers' (Director, Region 1) and Madden's discussion of the Federal Shoe Co. case and the Clark & Reid case C-128; significant correspondence concerning interstate commerce, includes memos from Nathan Witt to Madden, Carmody and Fahy with attached drafts of "Employees Directly Engaged in Interstate Commerce or Whose Activities Directly Affect Commerce" and the Standard Oil Co. of Indiana Case; from Gerhard Van Arkel to Fahy about the Fruehauf Trailer Co. case C-II and the effect of issuance of mandate on appeal by certiorari; correspondence relating to the Alaska Juneau Gold Mining Co. case, C-91; from Adolphus Andrews (Acting Sec. of the Navy) to Edwin S. Smith concerning the Wheeling Steel Corporation, and stating that the Navy does not discriminate against a contractor who fails to comply with the NLRA; from Beatrice M. Stern (Assistant Secretary, NLRB) to Captain H. E. Collins (Procurement Division, U.S. Treasury) about the International Filter Co., and the Treasury's judgement in awarding it a contract; correspondence concerning the International Merchantile Marine case R-24; correspondence regarding the Sailors' Union of the Pacific (SUP)-ISU controversy, includes a letter from Benedict Wolf to Aaron Sapiro stating that the Board will not take jurisdiction over conflicts between unions that are part of the same organization; from Philip Levy to Madden summarizing William Leiserson's talk on the effect of pre-existing agreements on Representation Disputes under the Railway Labor Act; from Wolf to E.S. Neal about the American Potash Co. C-127; significant correspondence concerning the William Randolph Hearst (Post-Intelligencer XIX-C-42) case includes discussion of strategy for Seattle hearings that will make it an interstate commerce case; letter from J. Warren Madden to the President concerning Edwin S. Smith; from Mortimer Kollender to Charles Fahy in regard to the Atlanta Woolen Mills case; from Howard Myers to Madden asking permission to publish his manuscript on the NLRA; from Charles Fahy to all attorneys on the status of litigation; from Baldwin B. Bane (Director, Registration Division) to Madden on Remington Rand Inc. File no. 2-2480; from Fahy to David Moscovits in regard to the Mackay Radio case and the Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals.
      - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 22)
        10/29/36-12/29/36; Correspondence relating to the LaFollette Committee Investigation, subjects discussed include: administrative issues, terms of cooperation with other government agencies, reaction to the LaFollette Investigation at the New York Democratic State Convention, the Black Legion and Virgil F. Effinger, information to be used for testimony on vigilantism, legal tactics to stall the LaFollette Investigation, the Tampa (A.F.of L.) Convention and a $200,000 appropriation; from Jerome I. Macht to J. Warren Madden on freedom of speech; from Philip Levy to Madden regarding the NLRA, the Railway Labor Act and the Texas Case, and Circuit Courts of Appeals Decisions on Constitutionality of the Act; from Beatrice Stern to C.A. Wood on Grace Line Seas Shipping Company hearing of 10/13/36; from Benedict Wolf about Teamsters organizing in Minneapolis, St. Paul and Milwaukee; Fahy on the status of Supreme Court litigation; Wolf's report on labor situations in Seattle, San Francisco, Los Angeles, and Cincinnati, subjects discussed include the maritime labor situation, A.F.of L.-C.I.O. confilct demonstrated by the Sawmill Workers' Union, and the San Francisco Chronicle`s coverage of the lettuce strike; Charlton Ogburn's and the President`s letters concerning his legislative program; argument in the Jones and Laughlin case (13pp); Philip Levy's conversation with Solicitor General Reed; Fahy's discussion of the status of Board cases in the Supreme Court and in the Circuit Courts; from J. Warren Madden to Charles H. Logan comparing the NLRA to the Railway Labor Act; from Fahy to Edwin S. Smith on injunctions; from Levy to Madden on congressional intention to apply the Act to production employees (7pp); Wolf's letter to the Civil Service Commission claiming the Secretary of the Board has direct supervision of trial examiners; letter from A.J. Wirin to Sidney Hillman; Charles Fahy's discussion of Supreme Court arguments, cases discussed include: Jones and Laughlin, Friedman-Harry Marks and Fruehauf; report from the Board to all attorneys, regional directors and trial examiners on investigations under Sec.9c, including elections, involving maritime workers (7pp); Edwin S. Smith's "suggested amendment of the National Labor Relations Act to provide for mediation in the maritime industry"; Wolf's request that speeches by regional directors be previewed by the Board; from Joseph Rosenfarb to the Board on state labor relations acts; from Blankenhorn to Madden on the following subjects: meeting Senator Guffey, the Carnegie-Illinois hearing, the Sun Shipyard Strike in Chester, PA; letter from William Green to Daniel J. Tobin (General President, International Brotherhood of Teamsters) concerning the Longshoremen's situation; Charlton Ogburn and Stanley Reed (Solicitor General) letters relating to the Washington, Virginia & Maryland Coach Co. case; from E.S. Neal (Region 20) to Wolf about the Salinas Lettuce Workers; Robert Watts'suggested 10 point amendment to the Act; Elinore Herrick's request to leave to investigate causes of the Spanish Civil War; Charles Hope's discussion of William H. Crawford; to all staff members defining subpoena, and discussing credentials and procedure.
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 23)
        1/4/37-2/16/37; Correspondence from Herber Blankenhorn to John L. Lewis, J. Warren Madden and the Board concerns the following subjects: John Brophy, the General Motors strike, the Carnegie-Illinois hearings, a reference to Myron Taylor as a "big fellow" before the LaFollette Committee, a Baby Act in the West Virginia, American Bridge Co., and "a Senatorial to-do over what to do"; letters between the President, the Attorney General and Charlton Ogburn includes discussion of the following topics: reactionary justice, Ogburn's, The Lawyer and Democracy, and a constitutional basis for social legislation; from Herber Blankenhorn to the Board and Denny Lewis (United Mine Workers of America) concerning the La Follette Committee hearings, includes discussion of funding, cooperation with the LaFollette Committee, Gelders, and Tennessee Coal and Iron; informal report from Charles A. Wood on Grace Line, Inc. and Panama Mail Steamship Co., and National Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association Local #33, case no.R-110; Witt and Francis H. Bohlen (The American Law Institute) letters regarding jurisdiction and craft unions; Wolf to trial examiners on hearsay evidence; transcript of conversation between J. Warren Madden and Frank Bowen about the General Motors strike; Joseph Rosenfarb's discussion of the attitude of the Court in reviewing acts of Congress; from Madden to the Attorney General requesting his opinion in the Oregon Worsted Co., a Corporation, and United Textile Workers of America, Local 2435; Elinore Herrick 's leave, in order to work for the American Labor Party; Malcolm F. Halliday to Madden in regard to United States versus Elgin, J.&E. Ry. Co., 298 U.S. 492; monthly report from Estelle Frankurter (Region 19) to the Board, includes references to the Mackay Radio decision and the Post-Intelligencer case; regional officers' comments on current labor situation for January, 1937 (13pp); memo to the Field Staff on cooperation with government agencies; George S. Wheeler's discussion of Respondent's brief, No.419 and distortions or inaccuracies in economic material; summary of Supreme Court Arguments from Robert Watts to all attorney.
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 24)
        3/3/37-4/30/37; Correspondence between the President and Charlton Ogburn includes discussion of Ogburn's '34 draft of a bill that could replace the NRA, and Salvador de Madariaga's Anarchy and Hierarchy; from Herber Blankenhorn relating to the La Follette Committee hearings, specifically the Harlen County hearings, E.C. Dunbar, Judge Feildelson and the Goodyear hearings, and "Suggestions to Mr. Lewis regarding the LaFollette Hearings"; from E.S. Neal regarding A.F.of L.-C.I.O. conflict; Dr. Edwin A. Elliott's (Region 16) "Observations on Labor Conditions in Sixteenth Region"; Blankenhorn's Senate Vote on Sit-Downs; E.S. Neal's discussion of National Motor Bearing Co. cases XX-C-126, and XX-R-79 contains a reference to "new employer tactics with regard to self-organization"; Madden to Henry Morganthaw Jr. (Secretary of the Treasury) in regard to awarding Remington Rand Inc. a contract pending a board decision; outline from David Saposs (Chief, NLRB Division of Economic Research) to Madden on bargaining unit, collective bargaining agency, selection of representatives in relation to majority rule (8pp); Madden to Nathaniel S. Clark (Director, Region 18) advising a secret ballot in the Sears Roebuck & Co. (case no. XVIII-R-42), contains a reference to communism; J. Warren Madden to S.D. Bland (Chairman, Committee on Merchant Marine and Fisheries) discussing a bill to amend the Merchant Marine Act of 1936, H.R.5193 (6pp); significant correspondence concerning the International Longshoremen's Association, and specifically the Longshoremen's Association of Hawaii, includes discussion of the Maritime Federation's opposition to the Guffey and Bland Maritime Bills, a report on a conference with Edwin Berman (representing the Longshoremen's Association of Hawaii), and preliminary report from H.R. Bridges (President, International Longshoremen's Association) to all locals assessing the strike, praising the C.I.O. and John L. Lewis, telegrams between Donald Wakefield Smith and Edwin S. Smith about the Hawaiian situation, and letters between Joseph P. Ryan (President, International Longshoremen's Association) and Madden regarding Charles Logan; from Herber Blankenhorn to Senator Thomas with a very short bibliography on labor in foreign countries; letter of apology from Beatrice Stern to Paul E. Hartsler concerning the Columbia Enameling & from Charles Fahy to Philip Levy considering possibilities to expedite enforcement of Board orders; record of telephone conversation between Madden and Senator Vandenberg about the NLRA, includes the Board's view on employer requested elections; from Madden to Maurice Howard forbidding him from union meetings (annotation says "not sent rep. 4-7-37") and revisions; from Joseph Rosenfarb to Genevieve Blatt (Executive Director, Intercollegiate Conference on Government), with catechism on labor legislation proposals; A.N. Somers' and Nathan Witt's discussion of the method of pleading commerce in complaint, subpoenas, and employers utilizing "rival" union as a spearhead to destroy a union selected by employees; from Louis J. Kleinklaus (Acting General Secretary-Treasurer, Commercial Telegraphers' Union-C.T.U.) to J. Warren Madden regarding a possible agreement between the International Merchantile Marine Co. (IMM) and the American Radio Telegraphers' Association (ARTA), specific attention to Elinore Herrick's role; from J. Warren Madden to Clara M. Beyer (Assistant Director, Division of Labor Standards, U.S. Dept. of Labor) relating to a proposed amendment to the Wisconsin State Labor Relations Act (amendment no.30s); from Erdahl to Charles Fahy on the National Association of Manufacturers and Chamber of Commerce analyses of Supreme Court's N.L.R.A. decisions; from Blankenhorn to John D. Moore anticipating ransacking Philip Easley's (National Civil Federation) files; to A.L. Wirin (Counsel, American Civil Liberities Union) opposing an amendment to the NLRA protecting agricultural workers; Will Maslow's "Does the NLRB have jurisdiction over the Consolidated Edison System of New York?"; from Towne Nylander to the Board on the Oregon Worsted case; Benedict Wolf's instructions for procedures involving compliance, jurisdiction, consent elections, exclusive bargaining, close case and formal papers; from Fahy to Madden reporting Jones' and Laughlin's noncompliance with the Board's order.Stamping Co. C-14; John P. Frey (President, Metal Trades Dept. A.F. of L.), and J. Warren Madden letters regarding representation of skilled and craft workers in mass production industries; from Charles Howard (Secretary, C.I.O.) to E.M. Weston (Secretary, Metal Trades Council Labor Temple) concerning the Seattle situation; Donald Wakefield Smith's discussion of El Paso Electric case and Globe Mail Service; form for commercial allegations in normal manufacturing cases; to the Attorney General in regard to the Growers-(?) Vegetables Association of Central California and unfair labor practices; personal and confidential, letter from Charles W. Hope to Madden discussing the Todd Seattle Drydocks, Inc. case, includes detailed account of individuals' actions
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 25)
        5/1/37-6/30/37; NLRB jurisdiction over Consolidated Edison Co.; Witt's discussion of cooperation with the Utah and Wisconsin State Labor Boards; Robert Watts (Associate General Counsel) and John B. Babe letters concerning Biles-Coleman Lumber Co. case, XIX-C-74; from Philip Levy and A.N. Somers to Fahy reporting arguments heard in the Santa Cruz and Carlisle cases; NLRB inquiry into office space available in the New Post Office Building; Malcolm F. Halliday to Fahy describing the National Metal Trades Association (NMTA), includes discussion of its organizational structure and jurisdiction, attached are summaries of the testimonies of Homer D. Sayre (Commissioner, NMTA) and James Matles (Grand Lodge Representative of International Association of Machinists); Robert Watts' discussion of litigation in the circuit courts, includes progress reports in the Remington Rand Inc. case; from Wolf to Cowdrill regarding noncompliance in the Columbia Enameling & Stamping Co. case (C-14); transcription of Senator Wagner's testimony before the Senate Committee on Education and Labor from Fahy; Clara M. Beyer and J. Warren Madden letters regarding the formation of a committee to discuss State Labor Relations and Mediation Acts; Blankenhorn's discussion of the LaFollette Committee hearings includes references to appropriations, the Railway audit and inspection of company offices and the Chicago Massacre; Ernest C. Dunbar regarding foregoing an investigation in the Weirton Steel Co. case VI-C-74; correspondence relating to A.F.ofL.-C.I.O. conflict includes a memo from Ralph A. Lind reporting as sit-down strike, a personal letter from Charlton Ogburn to J. Warren Madden concerning C.I.O. organizing in A.F.ofL. unions, a "red- hunting" campaign in the Southwest launched by the A.F.ofL. to discredit the C.I.O., a letter from Philip G. Phillips to Madden about the C.I.O. charging a company is in collusion with the A.F. ofL., and a monthly report from Charles Hope stating that the A.F.ofL. will not allow the management of the Post Intelligencer to deal with the C.I.O. (the American Newspaper Guild) and more; Nylander's (Region 21) request for consolidation of XXI-C-220, XXX-C-183 into XXI-R-101, a hearing of XXI-R-101 and the withdrawl of a petition to reopen XXI-137 in the Douglas Aircraft cases; from Blankenhorn to Madden and Robert LaFollette concerning the following topics: an Indianapolis speech, anti-labor policies in Hawaii, Army and Navy Intelligence in cooperation with industrialists, Sec.12b of Senator Black's New Bill (espionage), the Wages-Hours Bill, and the administration of the Steel Mediation Boards; discussion of election results and the reinstatement of striking engineers in the Panama Mail Steamship Co.; from the President to J.R. (?) with attached letter from Charlton Ogburn about his Federal Wages and Hours Bill; Madden and Charles N. Feidelson (Director, Region 10) letters regarding Virgil Finch; informal report from Region 10 on Mr. Googe's Intimations; John F. Milliken (President, United Licensed Officers of USA) and Elinore Herrick letters concerning the Clyde-Mallory Line case no. R-112; from Witt to Fahy about written agreements with respect to SWOC in Pittsburgh; Wolf's discussion of election procedures; from Fannie M. Boyles to Charles Fahy on the use of rubber stamp in issuing subpoenas; from Charles Hope to Donald Wakefield Smith about the Maritime and Woodworkers' situation; Joseph Lazarus' (Lawyer) account of Philip G. Phillips' behavior in the James F. Kane Co. Inc. case, also involves discharged employees and the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; from Edwin S. Smith to Nathan Witt concerning Calvert Magruder's "A Half Century of Legal Influence Upon the Development of Collective Bargaining", Harvard Law Review; from the Board to Regional Directors on elections and company unions; Elinore Herrick's response to the reorganization of regional boards and a discussion of S.2700 (Reorganization Bill); Nylander's request for a hearing in the Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Studio & M.P.P.A. et al XXI-R-149 to 158, XXI-R-172 to 182 cases; William Green's and Madden's discussion of the Interlaken Iron case decision; from Robert Watts to Mark Lauter concerning Republic Steel; from Robert Wholforth (Secretary, Subcommittee of the Committee on Education and Labor) to the Field Staff on cooperation with government agencies.
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        7/2/37-7/30/37; Letter from J. Warren Madden to Hon. Joseph T. Robinson (Chairman, Senate Select Committee) discussing S.2700 (Reorganization Bill), objecting to Sec.2c and Sec.204; from Philip Levy to Madden, and 2 drafts (1 annotated) of a letter from Madden to Hon. Hugo L. Black (Chairman, Committee on Education and Labor) opposing the Vandenburg amendments; A.F.of L.-C.I.O. conflict includes: a letter from Charlton Ogburn to Madden regarding elections brought by rival unions, a report from Philip G. Phillips on the H. Neuer Glass Co. case no.IX-R-57 and the Pittsburgh Glass Co. case no.IX-R-58, reports and a telegram from Charles Hope to Madden and Wolf on the Star Publishing Co. case no.XIX-C-141; memo from R.H. Kleeb (Region 6) to Wolf on the National Electric Co. cases no. VI-C-84 and VI-R-17; Estelle Frankfurter and Elinore Herrick discussion of weekly reports and excess work; Nylander's, and Fahy's discussion of interstate commerce and jurisdiction in the Metro-Goldwyn Mayer Studios cases; Fahy's discussion of the use of rubber stamp in issuing subpoenas; from Wolf to regional attorneys on adjurnments and reports on cases; Dr. John P. Boland's (Chairman, New York State Labor Relations Board), outline of the basis for cooperation and clearence between the State Board and the NLRB; from Wolf to Herrick on the International Merchantile Marine Co. case no R-24; letters to the President from Maury Maverick, M.C. (Member, Committee on Military Affairs, Subcommittee on Aviation, Congress of the U.S. House of Representatives) regarding the Administration's labor policy, Joseph P. Ryan's (President, International Longshoremens Association) request for an investigation into Mr. Smith's attitude toward the Barber Line Steamship Co.; Cowdrill's request for a hearing in the Republic Creosoting Co. case no. XI-C-122 after the company refused to reinstate discharged employees according to the seniorty clause of the strike settlement.
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        8/2/37-8/12/37; Fahy's discussion of increased workload and staff, the Vandenburg amendments, A.F.of L.-C.I.O. conflict, injunction suits, etc.; from Elinore Herrick to the Board about the International Merchantile Marine Co. case R-24; correspondence relating to A.F.of L.-C.I.O. conflict, and more specifically, Senator G.P. Nye's charge that the NLRB favors the C.I.O., includes discussion of the Combustion Engineering Co. case XIV-C-42, XIV-R-28, XIV-R-23 and the Gulf Oil Corporation, Port Arthur, Texas, case no.XVI-R-23 and no.XVI-C-78, from the Pittsburg Post Gazette, "Labor Board Convicts Self of Partisanship", H.E. Dozer (National Electric Products Corp., National "Firestop" Wires and Cables) to Hon. Robert L. Bulkley (U.S. Senator) claiming the NLRB is C.I.O. controlled, A. Howard Myers (Director, Region 1) to Madden alerting him to the possibility of an investigation of the New England Regional Office; from Madden to Wolf about the Tennessee Coal and Iron case; from Edwin S. Smith to Marvin H. McIntyre informing him that the telegram sent to the President from Joseph P. Ryan on 7/30/37 about Edwin S. Smith is untrue; from Clifford D. O'Brien to Wolf concerning "partisan language" in an intermediate report on the National Motor Bearing case, no.XX-C-126; correspondence relating to the Douglas Aircraft Co. Inc. cases XXI-C-183 and XXI-C-220 includes Nylander's discussion of trial examiner Rollin C. McNitt's handling of the cases with attached Los Angeles Times, "Douglas Case Has Flurry", and David Persinger's (attorney, Region 21) urgent recommendation that case XXI-C183 become a Board Case; from James C. Batten to Wolf finding the G. Sommers & Co. case no.XVIII-C-83 to be weak; from the Board (unsigned) to Hon. Richard B. Russel Jr. (U.S. Senator) concerning trouble with Mr. Curtis (former Atlanta Regional Board member) and Judge Feidelson and the Independent Union of Packing House Employees; correspondence concerning the Tupelo, Mississippi situation (Tupelo Cotton Mills Co. case and the Garment Co. case) includes Madden to Charles Logan disciplining him, and a reply from Gerhard Van Arkel (attorney) defending Logan, taking responsibility for Board action in Tupelo, includes a report of Ida Sledge's (ILGWU) efforts to organize, and the formation of armed vigilante bands; memo from Wolf to trial examiners on the conduct of hearings, stating trial examiners will not question witness; memo from Philip Levy to Charles Fahy about conflicting State and Federal Labor Relations Acts (33pp).
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)